Cool.
>> Hi everyone. Uh, welcome. Thanks for
joining us the textbook reading group.
And today we were going to look at
chapter 2 in the first half of the
textbook. Um,
and I I I gave this kind of introduction
of the book uh a couple weeks ago for
chapter 1 uh with with another sort of
group of folks. But uh a brief recap is
that the first half of the book is
essentially providing like uh sort of
theoretical foundations for active
inference and kind of covering a lot of
the various uh associated fields and
theories. So we introduced to the basian
brain hypothesis. We're um told about
predictive coding and message passing in
chapter 5 and all of these different
things. Marov blankets come up later. Um
and then it's in the second half of the
book that's more about direct modeling.
And so with what Daniel mentioned
earlier, I actually uh I'm curious about
what he it sounds like he just made
this. So probably a learning resource
that would be useful for anyone who's
interested in getting into the coding
themselves. Uh but yeah, so for for
chapter 2, uh following from chapter 1,
this is where we start taking the uh low
road to active inference. And this is uh
starting with sort of a basian
framework. Uh and so for those
unfamiliar,
um
Baz's rule is essentially a rule that
describes how we can find we can kind of
update uh our beliefs uh our prior
beliefs about a given phenomena given
that we have some kind of joint
distribution
uh which is a generative model that can
be used to predict phenomena.
So um whenever we take a joint
distribution for example the the
probability of X comma Y. So uh two
random variables x and y uh we we we can
kind of uh decompose that into uh this
this nice really sort of concise theorem
uh that is known as basis theorem that
if we are able to update particular
components of that then it allows us the
appropriate rules for updating the other
components such as uh if you have a x
representing beliefs about hidden states
of the world and you have why which is
observations received from that world
then based on new observations you can
then update your beliefs um so given a
new why you can update your beliefs
about X and the relationship between X
and Y that so that's that's the that's
sort of the general framework it's it's
used very broadly it's existed for for
decades it's used uh very commonly ly in
all kinds of fields, machine learning
like financial modeling uh very much
used in in neuroscience as well. Uh not
just in an active inference framework.
So so again it's is just kind of speaks
to the interdisciplinarity
uh of active inference is sort of the
depth of how far it's traced itself to
roots in various other fields. Um and so
the the the second chapter largely
sticks with that. we we get introduced
to other concepts such as um surprise
and basian surprise which are were which
are unfortunately and slightly
confusingly at first glance like they're
two distinct concepts. Um I I find them
interesting to think about in that uh
basian surprise would be taking uh the
what's called the coldback leler
divergence
uh between uh posterior distribution and
a prior distribution.
So it's kind of like saying okay we
received a new observation we update our
new beliefs our posterior beliefs. uh
how different are our new beliefs given
that observation versus uh our prior
beliefs that we had before we received
that observation. Uh if they're very
different that means a lot of belief
updating needed to happen. Uh right. So
what could happen is that uh they they
provide this as an example in the
textbook. Um but if you were to strongly
commit to a particular belief, if the
waiting was such that uh you know you
were you were fully convinced that uh
that you were not hungry, you are sad in
a in like a categorical probability
distribution of you know am I hungry? Am
I sad? Um like if you were fully
convinced that you were sated uh then
that means that if you received an
observation such as oh your stomach is
growling which would you know we could
speak about that like we might think
intuitively oh that would mean you're
you must be hungry right but if someone
were really fully convinced with like a
pro full probability of one that they
were sated regardless of any new
incoming observations then your outcome
your posterior beliefs will still be
that you are sad despite receiving that
observation. So, it's kind of like e
even though um even though you might not
expect to receive this observation that
that you you you know your stomach is
growling, you're still firmly convinced
that that you're sated and therefore no
belief updating happens. Um I so I I I
recommend looking at that. I think it's
in box 2.2. Um but but this idea of
basian surprise of how much belief
updating happens versus surprisal itself
which is a bit simpler. It's just the
marginal probability of a new
observation. So like given a generative
model how well does that model predict
that your stomach's going to growl you
know and that's it right? So that just
that so it has nothing to do with your
beliefs about uh if you're hungry or if
you're sad. It has nothing to do with X.
It's only the Y. So it's a which is why
we call it a marginal probability. Um
you know marginal meaning we kind of can
decompose the the model into just these
these marginal parts. So um so surprisal
is really just the negative log
probability of an observation that you
receive. So you could rece so so it
could be very surprising to you that
your stomach is growling and yet you are
highly convinced that you're you're
sated nonetheless. Right. Um
I like this example because uh for those
who are interested in the field of uh
computational psychiatry which there are
many who who come into this field um
come into active inference because
they're interested in or studying
computational psychiatry and are looking
to kind of add more tools to their
toolkit or another framework which I I
think that active inference is very it
it's it's very wide and I think it
brings a lot to computational
psychiatry. You can imagine that someone
who does not uh in everyday terms does
not listen to the new observations that
are coming in. You know, their stomach
is growling and yet they believe they're
sated. It it it's not terribly far away
from very common, you know, definitions
of what what it means to to uh have
delusional thinking or an inability to
update one's beliefs despite evidence to
the contrary, which uh is is kind of
widespread uh in a lot of uh sort of
psychopathologic like symptomatology,
right? So um you know someone with with
schizophrenia or someone who is
hallucinating who's fully convinced that
something is there uh whenever it's not
right or someone might tell them that
it's not but that you know thus
providing them with contradictory
evidence to their beliefs and yet they
still hold. So um it it's more difficult
in the case of hallucination because in
the case of hallucination you are in
fact receiving an observation that
something is there right. So it's just a
it's a reminder that this is not simply
a uh sort of preffrontal cortex uh only
sort of oh I just have to change the way
I think and I'll be fine. this this this
refers to kind of deeper like aberrances
in in the brain and in uh in sort of um
neuronal message passing, right? And so
things that can happen that can end up
producing a hallucination. So um that
that's that's why I kind of point to
like okay well you you can receive very
surprising observations and yet there's
no basian surprise in the sense that you
could still not update your beliefs,
right? So there's belief updating and
there's what the model actually
predicts. U those are sort of the core
some of the core aspects of uh kind of
understanding the low road to active
inference and and the the basian
framework and then it's in uh especially
later chapters chapter 4 uh where we're
introduced to expected free energy and
different breakdowns of free energy. um
chapter seven which starts talking about
matrices and and sort of these um
categorical probability distributions.
So actually taking Baz's rule and
actually putting it into uh a model that
goes beyond just having a likelihood.
So so chapter two is for anyone who's
new to a basian brain uh a basian
framework it it'll be a significant
amount to digest. uh for those who are
already familiar, they're not going to
receive anything too dramatically new
until they start getting into later
chapters and looking at how the basian
framework actually comes into more full
play um and active inference. I noticed
that someone uh someone's hand was up
over time and so u
>> yeah is is that okay if I I jump in? I I
think these you have great explanations
here and I really appreciate that. um
trying to get an understanding of how we
get from from bay to active inference.
But but the my question is is you were
talking about the kale divergence. I was
thinking of it as being the the distance
between your between the Q which is like
the approximate posterior and the actual
posterior. But if you're saying it's
that it's the difference between your
prior and the posterior, I can wrap my
head around that a lot better. It's just
sort of the cost of your belief
updating. Is it? But but I I maybe I'm
confused which is which is it is it the
prior to the posterior or is it the the
approximate posterior to the true
posterior?
>> Yeah. Yeah. No, I I see what you're
saying and it depends on like kind of
the the modeling situation at hand.
uh is how I would say that. So the the
formal uh kind of definition the way
it's described here is the posterior uh
and prior uh like that's what's given in
chapter 2. But then that said like um in
in whenever you're actually implementing
this within a model, it's there that it
becomes significant to look at the the
other uh perspective because in chapter
2, we're not actually yet getting into
variational methods, right? So we're not
looking at an approximate posterior. So
what you can do is that you can in in
very simple examples like the the frog
and the apple example that we're given
for example you can it's very
attractable to just directly compute
surprise and basian surprise right like
we you could do it by hand. Uh so it's
in those cases like there is no
variational
um posterior even computed in the first
place. You're just given it like an
exact posterior, right? So it's it's
whenever you start getting into using
the variational posterior that that this
kind of additional dimension of looking
at things and then actually if you could
if it were the case that like say your
model itself contains like what it
believes to be the the true uh you know
set of beliefs and then meanwhile you're
using this variational method to update
a variational sort of posterior then you
would do you could use KL divergence to
try and compare like but but that would
still be respective to that model like
does that make sense? Um yeah.
>> Yeah, I think so. Thank you so much for
clarifying that.
>> Yeah.
>> And when we get to the variational part
then I'll I'll probably have more
questions but for now this is this is
great. Thanks so much.
>> Yeah. No, absolutely. And I I totally
welcome questions and I think that
usually they end up providing a lot more
information to to other people who might
be considering the same thing. Um and
and yeah, it's that's that's sort of a
big move to start using variational um
methods in the first place. You're just
like kind of in a qualitatively
different paradigm. Even though doing
exact basian inference versus
variational basian inference, it's like
oh they share the basian inference part,
right? But but uh but yeah, once you
start using variational, it's like there
there's a couple additional assumptions
that get made along the way whenever
you're using variational methods. Uh for
anyone who's into computational modeling
and kind of like really breaking that
down thoroughly, that does mean that you
know unfortunately you do have to rely
upon a couple of extra uh assumptions in
order to view the outputs as is valid.
uh one way of of doing variational
basian inference is to use this kind of
active inference framework and the
particular ways that they do that. So
you'll see in later chap I don't think
they get into it in chapter 2 at all but
um later they'll start talking about how
free energy itself the way that sort of
works is a is a variational method is
that um using uh what's called Jensen's
inequality. So I I'll kind of speed it
up because it there will be more to get
into whenever you read about it in later
chapters. Uh but you it's kind of like
by using particular mathematical I
hesitate to call them tricks because
they're not tricks like they're like
proofs but still it's like by being able
to exploit particular um aspects of the
mathematics you're actually able to
create an upper bound on surprisal. And
so even though you can't directly
compute surprisal, you can at least
compute an upper bound on it. Uh meaning
like well if you can if you can continue
reducing that upper bound then you're
getting closer and closer to actually
minimizing your surprisal as well. Uh
for sure and so that upper bound is
itself free energy and it is tractable.
Right? So it's that's the entire
intention of using variational methods
is to just render a lot of these
computations tractable and possible and
perhaps even more efficient um than than
in cases where you just wouldn't be able
to because you're trying to do exact
inference. Um it's also very relevant
for those who who are concerned with
like biological plausibility of these
models. um it it fits really well with
different kinds of research in that area
because of course like the notion that
the brain computes exact basian
inference whenever we know that many of
these problems are not tractable just
doesn't hold up very well in like kind
of a realistic uh sort of setting. And
so part of the the biological
plausibility is is this uh aspect of the
theory or framework of active inference
that uh very we we there must be
something variational going on uh so to
speak, right? Being able to kind of use
mean field approximation and
marginalizing out different components
uh of a model and updating them, you
know, potentially separately or using
these intricate message passing schemes.
So the goal is to sort of render
intractable problems tractable while
simultaneously cohering with research
that has been done uh on the brain and
how message passing seems to occur, how
neurons seem to communicate with one
another. Um most research even outside
of active inference tends to view this
as like a kind of hierarchical message
passing process. there multiple systems
that are kind of passes passing
messages. So we have these kind of uh
descend and similarly the there will be
more kind of mechanical aspects of this.
Um, I think especially in chapters four
and five, uh, and definitely five for
anyone who's interested in actually like
aligning this with with, um, like deep,
uh, pyramidal cells and and and like the
kind of the more neurobiological
aspects. Um, feel free to skip ahead to
to chapter 5 if you feel like you have a
a comfort comfortable grasp of
everything prior to that chapter. Um but
but yeah, so so being able to kind of
have these these things cohhere with the
brain while simultaneously keeping
attractable um yeah is the gist. So um
anything else I would kind of highlight
about chapter 2 because it it's there
there's quite a bit going on and
actually I realize now we do get
introduced to um we do get introduced to
expected free energy already in chapter
2. um and we're introduced to
variational free energy. So um I'll I'll
just make a couple comments that that
both of them are variational methods. Um
so we do have variational free energy
and expected free energy. They are in
fact two different ways of computing
free energy.
uh variational free energy would be sort
of relative in real time to the model
given where it is at uh versus expected
free energy which hinted at by the word
expected is sort of a free energy of the
future so to speak. Expected free energy
is what's used whenever an agent uh does
what's called com uh computing policies.
So anyone who's uh familiar with
reinforcement learning that will become
or uh that'll be very apparent. Um like
whatever your intuition says it's
correct. Uh policies or you can think of
policies as actions or more precisely
sequences of actions. Uh right? So so if
you if you think of like a discrete case
like a a mouse in it in a team and it
can choose to go left or right. Um and
then there's also like another space it
could go to. So a policy might be, you
know, move to this part of the maze,
then move to the left arm of the maze
over the course of like two time steps
like sort of into the future, right? And
so that that doesn't involve um only
computing variational free energy in the
moment, but it actually also includes uh
predicting what will I expect in the
future. And that's where expected free
energy comes in and why it's relevant to
have this second um equation that is
it's highly related. They're both
variational. They're both using the same
components of the model which you can
liken to everyday concept. A likelihood
model is very similar to what allows us
to have perception. Um and then uh
having a state transition a state
transition matrix is very comparable to
the idea of just having a temporal
dimension having an understanding of
like well this le led to this so then I
can predict that this will happen next
if I do this like having that kind of
temporal dimension of of how you relate
things. Um so yeah with with expected
free energy um also important there is
that uh we can interpret expected free
energy a little bit differently than in
variational in that uh whenever we look
at
um
it's equation 2.6 and I apologize
usually I share my screen but I've been
having some issues with that today. Um
but equation 2.6 six, which is on page
33.
Um, and it's it's a bit of a a hefty
equation there, but it's really just
being broken down in uh multiple ways.
And I think especially that first line
where we're looking at um information
gain and pragmatic value. Uh,
interestingly, as opposed to variational
free energy where we really just think
of this as well, we're trying to reduce
complexity while improving accuracy. Um,
here with expected free energy, we're
trying to uh maximize two terms which
each of which are scored negatively.
They're both multiplied by negative one.
So technically by maximizing these
respective terms we're uh minimizing or
reducing the overall quantity whenever
we put them together uh and multiply
them by each by negative one and then
and then combine them. Um so information
gain uh and pragmatic value pragmatic
value is significant in that there's
this um this component C that we can see
there um the C is is a representation a
probability distribution uh of the
observations that the model expects
um just as a prior. So it's like a prior
over observations. So the way that this
is formalized in active inference is to
say that um
priors over observations they they tend
to get likened to the idea of
preferences and not necessarily
preferences in an arbitrary sense like
oh I I prefer this kind of dessert
versus this kind. Um preferences also
strongly relate to the notion of
something like homeostatic set points
for example. So, so if you had a kind of
continuous space like predictive coding
model um that had to do with an agent's
beliefs about its um you know blood
oxygenation levels, right? Or its heart
rate. Um
having preferences over sort of like
well- reggulated levels for those
different kinds of physiological
measures would be really crucial for the
agent's survival, right? Um, so being or
even just bringing up the the hunger
like the the the kind of slightly silly
but still very real um example I brought
up earlier of like your stomach growling
or not like we tend to prefer our
stomachs aren't growling. I again I
don't want to put it in such an
arbitrary sense because there's no
assumption that like you are like fully
um consciously rationally thinking of
things in this way. It can be that uh
different parts of the body, different
parts of the brain depending on how you
want to sort of divide up the marov
blanket as it were um each one of them
having their own kind of processes and
sort of inner model involved and have
their own sort of so to speak
preferences or priors over observations
that they would need to uh achieve
through action in order to maintain the
overall organism's survival. Right? So,
so the for those interested in like you
know sort of um chaos theory or dynamics
or just looking at like non-equilibrium
steady states this is very relatable to
the idea of an attractor right so so
whenever you take these these sort of
attractors or you know the the the brain
the body is attracted to you know having
the body at roughly 98.1 degrees uh
Fahrenheit uh you know is is a is sort
of normal normal or healthy um um you
know body temperature, right? Um that
figures into expected free energy and
saying like well expected free energy
ends up being scored over each of the
policies available to the agent. That's
what that that G parenthesis pi
represents. Pi is is your overall like
your policies your policy space. Each
potential policy gets scored by G. And
then we see that pragmatic value, that
difference between the actual
observations you expect given that
policy versus your overall preferences.
Basically, do I think taking this action
is going to get me what I prefer? Right?
Is is this action going to help me
achieve a regulated heart rate or a
sated uh you know hunger level or
stomach or or or you know level of glut
glutamate uh or or otherwise um or you
can think of it more whimsically like if
I go to this store will I be able to you
know get that dessert that I really like
uh right so that that's what kind of
pragmatic value is we want to maximize
it meaning like if I take this action
will I be able to expect that I will be
able to kind of get what I want or
realize my preferences or realize my
priors over observations that's why we
have that that that conditional
um the the just if if you ignore the the
expectation in the log it's just a
probability of a sequence of the
sequence of observations you expect if
you take this action conditioned on uh
and thus related to uh your preferences.
So essentially pragmatic value that
that's uh you know in reinforcement
learning you can almost think of that as
like that's sort of your reward function
right this is how the agent is able to
sort of plan and and figure out you know
if I ex you know if I take an action
what observations will I be able to
expect and then I can compare them to
what I actually want and that's kind of
how you score that uh meanwhile however
we also have information gain and this
is part of what attracts me uh like
myself and the the kind of work that
that I do because some of what I do
relates to uh reinforcement learning uh
in addition to computational psychiatry
um I've noticed in reinforcement
learning it's sometimes very difficult
to kind of handle the the so-called
explore exploit dilemma uh which is
where uh you know whenever you have a
model whether you're thinking of it as a
human being who you know might be
suffering from from some kind of um
mental um you know disorder or or
trouble or it could simply be you know
creating some kind of robot that
navigates a grid space or something. Um
it's difficult to say what should define
exploration and and for those who are
interested in philosophy there's always
this question of like well why don't
people just kind of you know get the get
as many resources as they need and then
just stay in their room you know that
that minimizes all potential surprisal
as much as possible right shouldn't
shouldn't that be what we do um of
course I would say like well if that
doesn't match your preferences then no
you won't do that uh and we don't tend
to prefer for uh staying in dark rooms
24/7, but it potentially for biological
reasons, but that's that's its own uh
conversation, I guess. U but all that is
to say that um with with active
inference, you you get this like kind of
nice formalized notion of what
exploration is uh and and it's already
included with pragmatic values. So where
whereas in reinforcement learning
what'll happen is people will focus on
what active inference calls pragmatic
value and then maybe you'll have some
kind of rule in there that says like oh
the agent should do something random 10%
of the time just to make sure it doesn't
get stuck in a local uh uh optimum right
like the idea of like you know
suboptimality is sort of relative to to
a model uh as well as to to the
observer, right? So so someone who
um you know in the case of schizophrenia
who is hallucinating, right? Like if
their brain is kind of computing that
hallucination as it were given that
their their their brain's makeup at that
time sort of the the the the kind of
figurative generative model that it's
working with to produce that
hallucination in a sense is kind of
optimal to that model despite from an
external observer's perspective say a
psychiatrist or or a therapist or or
just another person would say like oh
that doesn't seem correct relative to
the environment you're in. Right? So um
all all that is to say that um you know
we have pragmatic we we we
there there's the optimality that one
can kind of get stuck within right um
and so it's it's theorized that it's
through exploration that that people are
able to sort of get out of local optima
or find increasingly hopefully ideally
increasingly uh more optimal solutions
to to everyday problems. And that's sort
of a foundational aspect of adaptive
learning. So, um, so by being able to
actually have information gain as a
piece of this, uh, is kind of like
saying like this is how it's saying that
this is how the model works, but it also
says we're not just doing something
random. We're doing something that
actually continues to further the goal
of reducing surprise, of minimizing free
energy. Um it it so so it starts to to
kind of make more sense rather than just
viewing it as some kind of random number
generator process which is like quite
explicitly how that would be be done in
reinforce reinforcement learning models
on average. So with that that
information gain term, it's kind of um I
mean it's essent essentially just taking
the expectation of the the KL divergence
between uh you know here's what I so
it's it's a Q of X conditioned on Y and
pi
versus Q of X conditioned on pi. So we
already see like the only difference
between those two things is that y is
actually incorporated into that uh the
the first distribution of those two. So,
it's kind of like saying, well, here's
what I thought uh was going on or what I
what I think about the hit here are my
beliefs given uh here here's how I
believe my the hidden states of the
world relate to what I do, my policies.
Here's what I think I can do that
changes the world. However, here's now
what I think how I think that works
given the new observation. I'm
apologize. I kind of got myself in a
tongue twister there, but um it's just
to say like given this new observation,
what do I think about the relationship
between hidden states of the world and
what I can do? So that means that by
trying new things, you can try and
elicit new observations that can then
help you to learn more about the world,
right? Which is interesting because it
kind of conceptually it's almost like an
inversion of uh variational free energy,
right? with variational free energy,
it's like, well, we should be
self-evidencing, so we should just be
trying to do essentially the same
things. But but in that case, we we
never there's no guarantee that we'll
ever actually like um accomplish our our
goals uh or come closer to accomplishing
any kind of goals or preferences,
whether that be homeostasis itself or it
be, you know, a human being's like
long-term career trajectory or some
such, right? So, um that's sort of um
that's sort of the the the gist, uh the
overview of expected free energy and and
not just like how to sort of interpret
those first two terms, information gain
versus pragmatic value, but also kind of
understanding like this is a very um
kind of self-consistent process that
occurs that doesn't rely upon sort of
random processes, right? like you you
can try it you can include like an error
term uh in different places with
predictive coding models like this is
the unexplained variance but um but
there's no forced like oh 10% of the
time do something random and that's sort
of the what some would argue would be
the sort of elegance of of planning in
an active inference scheme as opposed to
you know comparison to some others Mark
yeah you had your hand up again if you
want to go for
Sorry, I was on mute there for a second.
Yeah, thanks. Uh, this is just another
great explanation. I just want to make
sure I understand this. So, when we talk
about expected information gain, right,
we're we're talking about the the
distance between again sort of like
prior beliefs about policies uh and and
the posterior beliefs about policy. So
like as the farther these are apart uh
the greater information was gained
through but through the through the
update and that is then inversely
proported
to the free energy. Is that right? So
there's a negative sign. So the so the
the more I learn I guess the the bigger
the update the
smaller the free energy. Is that right?
So I I've resolved uncertainty. Is that
a fair way to look at it?
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. So
>> Okay. Okay. So I was thinking of it in
terms of like there's a there's a cost
there there's entropy associated with
that belief update though. Is is that
right? Am I maybe I'm conflating.
>> No, you're you're
>> because I'm almost there, I think.
>> Yeah. No, you're totally fine. And in
fact, I mean, you know, again, looking
at the entire equation, it's like there
are other ways of kind of sort of
breaking this up. And then you see like
with expected ambiguity immediately
below that h like that is where we are
explicitly like looking at this in terms
of like kind of entropy functions. Um
but but if we just constrain it to
looking at it as information gain first
off yes you're absolutely right the I
the idea is that if you if you sort of
maximize or increase information gain if
you learn more about the relationship
sort of between the world and
observations and and policies given that
there's a negative sign there that does
mean that the more we increase
information gain the more expected free
energy will decrease. um to put to
briefly put that into the perspective of
some of what I was saying earlier um if
free energy is an upper bound on
surprise right then we're going to want
to minimize uh free energy so in this
case by learning more you would indeed
be reducing free energy and then from
reducing surprisal right so it's I mean
it's um we also remember like you could
improve information gain like immensely
yet simultaneously have like virtually
no pragmatic value, right? Like um
oh I almost want to say like trigger
warning or something, but I realized I
came up with like a very dark example,
but it's like well someone doesn't know
what it's like to you know I'll I'll
lighten it up a little bit but it's
still a bit dark. Uh, someone doesn't
know what it's like to be unconscious.
So, they're like, "Well, I could knock
myself out, right?" Like, is that you
could learn a lot? Maybe, maybe not. You
realistically, no. But, but someone
could have that belief if you just kind
of localize it to this is their thought
space right now. Uh, this is sort of
their generative model and the problem
they're trying to figure out. Like, is
it truly worth it to do that in order to
learn that, right? Um so so if it's if
the answer is no or or at least if that
the way that policy of knocking yourself
out uh if that scored much lower than
than u or much worse off so to speak has
much higher expected free energy than
than another policy which says well
don't do that you know it's at least you
get to stay alive and conscious and all
of that. uh you know that that the the
pragmatic value of not doing that uh far
out seek uh exceeds the information that
you might gain from uh from doing this
silly thing um then ultimately you don't
do the silly like you right so so that's
um sort of a crude way of saying that
it's like the so given that this is
scored over all policies which is
another significant issue and why we use
variation like the significance of using
variational methods not just for bi
biological plausibility but you know
imagine that there a plethora of
something that of actions or policies
that an agent could take right and every
single one of them is getting scored so
that there could be a ton of
possibilities that are getting scored
all simultaneously right and so for
every single one of them there is an
information gain term and uh and a
pragmatic value term so at one point in
the the textbook and and some people
have interpreted this differently and so
uh Daniel and I will frequently like
make a comment on this. At some point in
the textbook they claim that that uh
with active inference and kind of
planning is inference and their
framework. They say that uh sort of
exploration and exploitation quote
unquote naturally balance uh one
another. And that's that's not exactly
right because you could still have a lot
of information gained but zero pragmatic
value, right? Um as in the silly example
I gave a minute ago of someone knocking
themsel out or something. Um you could
have a full a very pragmatic very high
pragmatic value and no information gain
which someone who follows a routine can
like kind of intuit it. It's like, oh,
this is a very helpful routine and I'm
not diverging from it, so I'm never
really learning anything new, but uh
it's because it works for me, right? Or
maybe you arrived at that policy and
kind of chiseled it out over time. It's
like this is what my ideal day would
look like, or this is what the ideal
series of steps or actions I would take
over the course of day would look like.
Maybe with some various degrees of
divergence, maybe with various degrees
of like, you know, some something could
come up or, you know, an unexpected
events, a call on the phone, a meeting
was canceled or otherwise I could get
sick. But, um, you know, any of that.
But the idea is sort of planning is
inference here is just sort of over time
being able to sort of discretise time
into a sequence of steps and thinking of
uh for each of these potential sequences
of steps what is there to be gained and
what is there to be learned
most sort of intuitive sense that's how
I would say
they do.
So a lot of these these kinds of
concepts that we're introduced to on so
on page 37 they figure 2.6 six they
tried to essentially show again with the
sort of interdisiplinary aspect of
active inference uh its relation to to
other fields and so we there are aspects
of like control theory here in
cybernetics whenever there's economics
is implicated whenever we're talking
about risk um so I wasn't going to break
any of this down too explicitly but in
part because they already kind of do
that themselves but I was just going
refer to this for anyone who's
interested in tying this into sort of
other fields and uh yeah sorry I team I
noticed your hand was up
>> yeah thank you thank you for the great
explanations uh I I wanted to track back
a little bit and maybe have I have a
question about the definition that they
that they introduce at the end of
chapter 3 uh which is related to
expected uh expected free energy and
they say that uh a generative model when
endowed temporal depth opens the door to
the minimization of expected free energy
which uh entails at least a primitive
form of agency. So uh as I understand it
like the capacity to model alternative
futures and to select among them to
minimize expected free energy is uh
basically what agency is what a how
agency is defined is is there like more
to it? uh is is like just the planning
and the the the the vision of the f the
the the modeling of the future. Is it
the the only prerequisites for for
defining agency in this framework or are
there more or or do they go into more
details into into how agency should be
defined should be uh should be
conceptualized and uh maybe this is more
of a philosophical question that is
maybe out of scope for this uh
discussion group. uh how does this
relate to free will? uh does uh does it
is is the capacity for planning and uh
and prospection is it a sufficient basis
for what we understand as free boil oil
is is there something more that is
required but this is not you don't have
to answer the second question I really
the more important question I have is is
really how agencies defined and uh and
uh and if if they go into more details
on this because it's what interests me
uh right now I want to really get the
sense of how agency can be defined and
how it can be useful for us to to model
like for example AI systems.
>> All all really good questions and the
way that you kind of um kind of uh kind
of laid all of that out in that
sequential order everything made sense.
Um so
I'm
first it is I do think it's a a bit of a
philosophical topic. Um that is not to
say that those who engage in active
inference should not
engage in philosophy. It's a major topic
and there are many people who are
interested in active inference who want
to discuss notions of agency, free will,
uh consciousness, what does it mean to
like plan or deliberate uh and things
like that. I think that it's been sort
of conceptualized in various ways uh
even within active inference. I think
that people are kind of publishing on
this uh in different ways. Uh but many
people have kind of commented on it. Um,
I might be able to find a couple things
I could share in the the chat, but there
are those like uh Enasi Bolito who uh
you know or or um um I think even Chris
Fields who's actually someone who
doesn't Enesso is a a philosopher uh
first and foremost who who's written
broadly on active inference and kind of
discusses some of these things and there
are a lot of authors uh sort of in that
maloo who will also use it to comment
upon uh AI and conceiving of AI and what
would it mean to to have agency. I would
say um this this uh this segment that
you pointed out here in the in the
textbook which is on uh page 59 for for
um anyone who's interested in this uh
which we also remember that's in chapter
3 which is the high road which is kind
of starting from sort of what it means
well let's not say means but what what
it is to be an organism and to continue
to exist uh like adaptively
survive, right? So, it would I think
that's part of why they do this like
high versus low road. The low road being
like a very almost strictly mathematical
basian framework from the whenever you
first start and then it's just from
there that you can start viewing that as
sort of like how we could model
cognitive functions including perception
and action and decision making versus uh
the the other direction which is sort of
like how do organisms persist. Um and so
here we're looking at this from a very
kind of organismic uh perspective. And
then we get this comment on um having a
you know potentially a minimal form of
uh or primitive form of of agency. Um,
and I think just from what I can say is
that because I while I'm very interested
in philosophy, I tend to do a lot of
kind of computational modeling uh and
and and focus sort of more on on on that
and relating it to sort of mechanistic
processes. Um,
from from sort of a hardline perspective
that would say like no, there is no
agency. Um I'm not so willing so freely
able to say that. I don't I don't feel
comfortable even though like that's not
the way I should be saying that like
that everything's intuition now.
But um but yeah, I mean it's if if you
were able to say like well there are
particular kinds of processes involved
here they tend to play out you know
aside from some stochastic you know
error that happens here or there noisy
observations it's otherwise generally
you know deterministic or
semi-deterministic
the idea of agency does sort of sort to
kind of fall out of view. Um that said
though I mean the the authors here
themselves are saying that there is a
form of agency I so another way of
framing it could be like well if you
looked at a model that had no capacity
for planning uh and then you just stay
within this active inference framework.
So for example we just went over
expected free energy. Uh expected free
energy is necessarily like a form of
kind of planning. uh that form of
planning relates to certain kinds of
homeostatic set points that one holds.
So preferences that were related in that
C matrix your attractor. So if you
totally remove uh any kind of attractor
from a system that means that it's not
attracted towards anything in
particular. Well, whenever you put that
into a sort of biological environment
where
like ideally it would be uh you know if
you remove any kind of attractor from a
person then suddenly like they don't
necessarily have any reason to their
model can't infer that they have any
reason to eat food to sleep you know to
take care of themsel in any way shape or
form. Uh and so you know kind of in
physical terms like without some kind of
attractor and capacity for realizing
that sort of attracting state uh in some
way shape or form you you just kind of
fall into entropy right you you
dissipate within your your environment.
Um that's uh that relates to a notion in
active inference and really a lot of
other computational modeling in general
whether it's active inference or or not.
But it's all to say like an organism
doesn't necessarily have to have a set
of beliefs that perfectly match its
environment. It just needs to have the
right equipment for navigating that
environment well enough to to realize
the attraction. So I I'm afraid I'm
getting just a little distanced from
from your your query, but it's just to
say that I do think maybe the way they
frame it here makes sense. The idea of
if you're able to kind of predict a
little bit more into the future for
making different kinds of decisions,
right? Because I even in like social
theory or social sciences or things like
that or philosophy people uh one one way
of framing agency would be to say like
well if if you have no actions available
to you and you have no way of trying
like being allowed to choose from
different available actions uh for
whatever your own purposes are then you
don't have agency. Um, and and for those
who aren't even trying to take it from a
philosophical standpoint, maybe even
more of a legal standpoint like you or
or or or moral standpoint, like you
shouldn't remove someone's capacity,
their agency, right? Everyone should be,
you know, someone might make a claim
that everyone should be entitled to some
level of agency. That usually does refer
back to the general idea of being able
to have actions that are available to
you and you get to freely choose. In
that case, planning would be a form like
having a capacity for planning and
action would be directly related to an
idea of having agency. Um, I feel like
if I were to speak anymore though, I I
would I might as well just like write an
essay or something. Uh, so so that's
that's kind of where I'll leave that.
But um, I would definitely even just a
few Google searches between active
inference and agency or free will and
things like that. There are many people
who have been very interested in this
topic. It's just not my particular like
area of expertise. So yeah,
>> thanks a lot. But I see that there's
some interest in the chat and I'm also
interested. Could you share the the name
of the authors because I I didn't get
the you said Polito or Chris Fields and
PTO.
>> Yeah. Yeah, for sure.
While I'm doing that, if anyone else has
any
thoughts or questions they want to bring
up, we can can definitely get to that,
too.
This may be off topic, but there is a
paper that's co-author. I mean, Carl is
the first author on this um active
inference and intentional behavior. Um,
and I don't know if that's
like you said, it's uh um it's
maybe not exactly the thing you're
thinking about, but um it does discuss
the difference between reactive,
sentient, and intentional behaviors and
simulations. So, I mean there is it's
it's not in the textbook, which I know
is the topic of this conversation, but
um yeah, I just thought I'd mention
that.
>> Totally. And thank you for for sharing
that. Um and it I just looked it up
myself and the way you described it too.
It very much it very much
having not read it myself it very it
seems to very much relate to the
textbook which the textbook in a sense
is just sort of like a snapshot of sort
of where folks like Thomas Parr and Carl
Friston were at in their research over
the preceding decades like up to that
point in time and uh and Daniel and I
are frankly at this point looking
forward to this new textbook that will
be published next year which I think
will just include a lot more that's uh
been written since. Um but yeah, I mean
with with intentional behavior and the
way that you described like or mention
like um and that's something I didn't
bring up and maybe should have, but if
we imagine an organism that doesn't have
a capacity for planning, it then would
become a much more sort of reactive
organism
and uh and we would view it as maybe not
having agency or we would view it as not
having intentional behavior. Uh so one
one kind of simple example of that is to
think of like a thermostat like a
control system. It's just it in that
case a thermostat does have uh a
homeostatic set point so to speak. We
won't say it's homeostatic but we'll say
it is a set point uh quite literally
like that is its design. uh and so if
the temperature that it reads in the
room as its incoming observations
um if that you know falls below the stat
point then the agent the thermostat
increases the temperature right but in
that case it's reactive so it doesn't
have to do with uh any kind of sort of
you know I believe that if I do this
then this will happen uh it's more of a
strict like on a momentby-moment basis
uh like purely reactive system right
now. What someone could do is like
program some kind of decision-making
process within it to where oh uh you
know over the next hour I'll heat up you
know the thermostat will increase the
temperature by one degree and then the
following hour it'll increase it by 3°
and then after that it'll reduce it by
two degrees and that's a particular
sequence of actions defining a policy
and each one of them can get scored
relative to some kind of attracting
state like if it were to become more
complex then it would start to kind of
look like planning under active
inference or even just planning as
inference as a general scheme. Uh would
someone want to attribute intentional
behavior to that or agency? Um I think
it's around there that like you know
there are those who might disagree with
one another uh over how that should be
how that should be viewed. So it's
around there that I'm like, yeah, it
really depends on how you want to define
uh agency or intentional behavior. But
many organisms are in fact reactive,
right? Like a lot of um kind of microc
cellular organisms are essentially just
sort of floating in their respective
spaces and like immediately reactive to
any kind of nutrients that start to
touch them or something along those
lines, right? Like not necessarily a
capacity for planning involved. Um, so
it it's a very interesting topic uh to
me to say the least. I just don't have
any definitive statements on what is
agency.
Um, and then I'll just share
I'll try to think of any others that
that might come up. Um,
and
there's um this is sort of
uh
a quick way of sharing
some of these things. But there there
have been for for anyone who just kind
of wants some some listening material.
Um there was last year a nice series
called active inference insights. I just
shared the link to it. It's on like
streaming services etc as well. But so
so there are various figures um that
were that were interviewed um uh by uh
guy Darren who was involved with the
institute previously and so he's done
talks with um Carl Fristen and and um
some other big figures in the area Mark
SS Ian McGillicest who's a psychiatrist
and others and so there there's a lot
going on Alexander Rorbia who's more
into robotics and reinforcement
learning. So, it's there's kind of a
nice diversity of voices uh from from
different fields and um and some of them
are certainly much more sort of on the
philosophical side. There's Vanjese who
discusses uh consciousness but relates
it to information theory but also
ethical AI. Um so I would have a look at
that. I think that's probably the the
quickest thing I could share with you
all in a single link. Um and then of
course all of them have their own
respective publications if you want to
dive deeper. Um but uh so I see that uh
we we really hit time here but um I hope
that this was helpful to some of you who
are still considering uh you know some
of the the topics here and the the
equations or formalisms or otherwise for
those who are still you know kind of
interested in the mathematics uh and and
breaking that down further. There will
be much more to come in the in the
coming chapters. Uh even more so in the
second half of the book whenever we
start seeing particular uh p what they
do is that they take different kinds of
active inference simulations that have
already been sort of coded up
computationally and published. And so
what they do is use those as sort of
learning heristics for understanding
these different models. Um and so so
that'll figure strongly in the second
half of the book. Uh there's also the
append appendix in the back of the book
that uh this is the author's own take on
trying to sort of describe some of the
basics to probability theory such as
what is the product rule or moving up to
to sort of linear matrix operations that
we see in uh discrete time models and um
just you know essential calculus and
taking derivatives and so on. So um
there are many resources like
essentially in the back of the book and
then it's uh you're just a step away
from from further learning those things
on your own if you want to get any
deeper from there. Uh and then yeah the
the next session next week at this time
we'll we will switch over to the other
cohort but anyone who is here is welcome
to join. We'll talk about chapter 7
which is where we'll um or excuse me
that yeah uh we'll talk about chapter 7
and that will be about discrete time
models. Um so a lot of the dynamics that
we saw here will actually play out.
We'll have a likelihood uh distribution.
We will have state transitions and we'll
have planning uh as as those models they
they all have this kind of temporal
dimension and a capacity for planning
and decision- making and perhaps even
agency. Uh so um yeah, I welcome you all
to that and uh thank you all for for
coming today and we'll we'll wrap it up
there.
>> Thanks so much. Andrew, when when are
you doing chapter 3? It sounds like
you're switching over.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. There's uh so uh
Daniel and I do this sort of
alternating. Unfortunately, it's always
a little confusing to ex like describe
to people quickly, but it's essentially
uh there's a morning and an evening
session relative to I'm in the United
States. So, um thinking that those time
zones u the in he always does the
morning, I do the evening. Um so, two
weeks from now, it'll be chapter three
with this cohort. So, it's sort of we we
it's sort of just this uh back and
forth. Um,
>> so you'll be in the morning on the next
Thursday. Then you're just going to
continue to flip up more or less.
>> Yeah, I will always do the evening
because that's when I'm available. But
the
essentially the other cohort is doing
the second half of the book and then
this cohort is doing the first half. So
we have this kind of odd zigzagging
between, you know, there it'll be uh
next week it'll be chapter 7 for second
half of the book. week after that would
be chapter three, then chapter eight,
then chapter four. You see this kind of
back and forth like that. But the idea
is that it sort of allows us to have two
separate cohorts going simultaneously
for a session before we take another
month or two long break. Um, so it just
kind of it's a bit of a speedrun, I
guess, in that sense. But, um, anyway,
yeah, so two weeks from now, chapter 3.
All right. Thanks so much, everyone.